Guide to the Stanford University, President's Office, Sterling-Pitzer transitional records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, President's Office, Sterling-Pitzer Transitional Records
1946-1970
1964-1970
SC0217
Stanford University. Office of the President
15 Linear feet (10 boxes)
These records were generated during the tenure of President Kenneth Pitzer as well as his predecessor J. E. Wallace Sterling. Records are arranged in the following sequence: committees, academic and administrative departments, general files, and materials pertaining to the Stanford Research Institute. Other subjects of note in the general files include the House Un-American Activities Committee, Women’s Social Regulations, 1965-68, and Card Stunt at the Air Force Football Game, 1966.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
J. E. Wallace Sterling, Stanford's fifth president, served from 1949 through 1968. Kenneth Pitzer took office on December 1, 1968 and served until September 1970.
Description of the Collection
These records were generated during the tenure of President Kenneth Pitzer as well as his predecessor J. E. Wallace Sterling. Included are files on committees, academic and administrative departments, and the Stanford Research Institute, as well as general administrative files. Subjects of note in the general files include the House Un-American Activities Committee, women's social regulations, 1965-68, and the card stunt at the Air Force Football Game, 1966.
Arrangement note
Records are arranged in four series: Committees, Academic and Administrative Departments, General Files, and Stanford Research Institute Files.
Access Terms
Pitzer, Kenneth S., (Kenneth Sanborn), 1914-1997; Stanford Research Institute.; Stanford University. Office of the President; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; Women college students.
Collection Contents
- Committees, Series 1
  - Academic Council Committees, 1968-69 (Box 1)
  - Academic Council Correspondence, 1963-66 (Box 1)
  - Academic Council minutes, 1967-68 (Box 1)
  - Academic Council, Executive Committee minutes, 1966-68 (Box 1)
  - Academic Senate, 1968-69 (Box 1)
  - Academic Senate, 1967-68 (Box 1)
  - Admissions of Humanities and Sciences, (ad hoc) Committee, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Admissions, undergraduate Committee, 1966-67 (Box 1)
  - Advisory Board (Box 1)
  - Advisory committee, University, 1968-69 (Box 1)
  - Appellate Board, Special (inactive), 1967 (Box 1)
  - Archives, University, Committee, 1965-66 (Box 1)
  - ASU Finances, Ad Hoc Committee (terminated), 1970 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Committee (terminated), 1966-69 (Box 1)
  - Athletic committee, 1965-69 (Box 1)
  - Athletics, Committee on (Mr. Glover's file), 1968-69 (Box 1)
  - Biology, Ad Hoc committee on Long Range plans for, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee on University Policy (COUP), miscellaneous correspondence, 1962-68 (Box 1)
  - Dinkelspiel Awards, Committee on, 1959-65 (Box 1)
  - Educational Opportunities for Disadvantaged Minorities, 1964-66 (Box 1)
  - Executive committee Nominating Committee, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Educational Program, Stanford, Planning Committee for the Study of (terminated), 1966-67 (Box 2)
  - External Awards Committee (Marshall Scholarship Committee), 1964-68 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Housing, Sub-committee on, Minutes (Land and Building Development), 1966-69 (Box 2)
  - Fulbright Scholarship Committee, 1960-61 (Box 2)
  - General Studies, Committee on, correspondence, 1961-67 (Box 2)
  - General Studies, Committee on, minutes, 1965-68 (Box 2)
  - General Studies Advisors, 1960-64 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Division, Committee on, 1966-68 (Box 2)
  - Health, University, Committee on, (terminated 1969), 1966-69 (Box 2)
  - Interfraternity Board, 1961-66 (Box 2)
  - Land and Building Development, Advisory Committee on, 1967-69 (Box 2)
  - Land and Building Development, Advisory Committee on, minutes, 1966-67 (Box 2)
  - Military Programs, Committee on, 1959-61 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Committees, (Sarah Stephanson's file), 1966-67 (Box 2)
  - Overseas Campus, Academic council Committee on, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Parent's Day coordinating committee, 1962-65 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Committees 1967-68 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Committees, Students on, 1962-66 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Committees-Lists, etc., 1963-66 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Committees-Work Sheets, Mr. Glover, 1962-63 (Box 2)
  - Public Exercises, Committee on (Mr. Glover's file) 1968-69 (Box 2)
  - Public Exercises, 1965-67 (Box 2)
  - Public Exercises, Sub-Committee on Camp and West Lectures, 1960-62 (Box 2)
  - Public Exercises, Sub-Committee on Commencement and Baccalaureate, 1961-66 (Box 2)
  - Public Exercises, Student Guide Service, 1956-63 (Box 2)
  - Registrar's Advisory Committee, 1969-70 (Box 2)
  - Religious Affairs, Council on, 1960-62 (Box 2)
  - Ecumenical Council for Stanford, 1962 (Box 2)
  - ROTC, Ad Hoc committee on (terminated), 1968-69 (Box 2)
  - Stanford Alumni conference, Faculty Committee, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Student Health, Committee on, 1962-65 (Box 2)
  - SLAC Coordinating Committee, 1966-68 (Box 2)
  - Students on Committees, 1963-66 (Box 2)
  - Summer Schools (University of Birmingham, London, Oxford and Scotland), Joint Committee for - Advisory Committee, 1965-68 (Box 2)
  - Tresidder Union Committee (terminated), 1966-69 (Box 2)
  - Voluntary Stanford Organizations, Sub-Committee on, 1963-64 (Box 2)
- Academic and Administrative Departments, Series 2
  - Admissions, Director of, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Admissions (General) 1966-70 (Box 3)
  - Admissions A-H, 1966-67 (Box 3)
  - Admissions I-Z, 1966-67 (Box 3)
  - Admissions - Graduate, 1966-67 (Box 3)
  - Admissions - Graduate, 1965-67 (Box 3)
  - Admissions, Transfer, 1966-67 (Box 3)
  - Aeronautics and Astronautics (School of Engineering), 1963-68 (Box 3)
  - Aerospace Studies (Air Force), 1966-68 (Box 3)
  - Art and Architecture, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Art Dept., New Building for (Box 3)
  - Business, Graduate School of, 1967-68 (Box 3)
  - Business Office - Staff/Project Planning - minutes, 1969-70 (Box 3)
  - Business Office - Staff/Project Planning - minutes, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Business Office (V.P. for Business Affairs), 1967-68 (Box 3)
  - Computer Science, Visiting Committee, 1968-69 (Box 3)
  - Dean of Students, 1965-68 (Box 3)
  - Earth Sciences, School of, 1967-68 (Box 3)
  - Earth Sciences, correspondence re new building, 1966-68 (Box 3)
  - Earth Sciences, Visiting Committee, 1966-68 (Box 3)
  - Education, School of, 1966-69 (Box 3)
  - Engineering, School of, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Finance, V.P. for, building priorities -- Plant Fund Allocation, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Financial Aids, 1965-69 (Box 3)
  - Food Service, 1967-68 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Visitors office (terminated Sept. 1970), 1970 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Division, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Hoover Institution, 1967-69 (Box 3)
  - Hopkins Marine Station (Te Vega) (Box 3)
  - Humanities and Sciences, 1966-69 (Box 3)
  - Humanities and Sciences Committee Meetings, 1968-69 (Box 3)
  - Humanities and Sciences (Special Programs), 1967-69 (Box 3)
  - Law School, 1967-68 (Box 3)
  - Law School, Board of Visitors, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Law School, Semester Plan, 1964-65 (Box 3)
  - Libraries, 1968-69 (Box 3)
  - Medicine, School of, 1967-69 (Box 3)
  - Medical School New Building, 1966-68 (Box 3)
  - Medical School Visiting Committee, 1968-69 (Box 3)
  - Memorial Church, 1966-69 (Box 4)
  - Military Science, 1965-69 (Box 4)
  - Music, 1968-60 (Box 4)
  - Naval Science, 1966-69 (Box 4)
  - Overseas Campus program (and directory) 1968-69 (Box 4)
  - Overseas Campus program: Stanford in Austria, 1966-69 (Box 4)
  - Overseas Campus program: Stanford in Germany, 1966-68 (Box 4)
  - Physical Education and Athletics, 1967-69 (Box 4)
  - Physical Education and Athletics: Athletic Board, 1967-69 (Box 4)
  - Physical Education and Athletics: Football, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Physical Education and Athletics: Pat Morrison Affair (personal appearance standards); P.E. Dept. clippings, policy, general info, 1966-68 (Box 4)
  - President’s Office 1968-69 [empty folder] (Box 4)
  - President, Consultant to, (Terman) 1966-68 (Box 4)
  - Vice-Provost, Herbert L. Packer, 1966-69 (Box 4)
  - President Pitzer, Special Assistant to (Willard Wyman), academic year 1969-70 (Box 4)
  - President’s Office, fire in, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Research Administration, 1968-69 (Box 4)
- General Files, Series 3
  - Administrative Search, 1966-July 1968 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Almanac, 1967-69 (Box 5)
  - Stanford (Alumni) Clubs, 1967-68 (Box 5)
  - East Bay Stanford clubs, Oakland woman’s club, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Bakersfield, 1960-62 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Boston, 1966-67 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Chicago, 1962-67 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of New York, 1957-67 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Orange County, 1960-67 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Phoenix, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of San Francisco (Box 5)
  - Alumni Club of Tokyo, Japan, 1960-66 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Clubs – football films (carry), 1957-59 (Box 5)
  - Alumni conference, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Alumni conference, 1969 (Box 5)
  - [Alumni] Stanford conference – Southern Calif., February 16, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Americans Building Constitutionally (ABC) (Box 5)
  - American Council on Education meetings in San Francisco, 1966 (Box 5)
  - American Universities Field Staff, 1954-64 (Box 5)
  - Applications (Non-Military) re: teaching, 1961, 1967-69 (Box 5)
  - Applications (Not-Defined) A-L, 1968-69 (Box 5)
  - Applications (Not-Defined) M-Z, 1968-69 (Box 5)
  - Applied Electronics Laboratory / Encina (et. al.), correspondence, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Articles, 1968-69 (Box 5)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University, election, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University, constitution, 1965-69 (Box 6)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University President Dennis Hays, 1968-69 (Box 6)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University President Cesare Massaranti, 1967-68 (Box 6)
  - Associated Students of Stanford University President Peter Lyman, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1965-67 (Box 6)
  - Association of College Admissions Counselors, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges, 1963-65 (Box 6)
  - Association for Higher Education, 1964-67 (Box 6)
  - Association of Independent California Colleges and Universities, 1965-69 (Box 6)
  - Cabinet, Stanford, 1968-69 (Box 6)
  - California Committee to Legalize Abortion, 1966 (Box 6)
  - California Dept. of Fish and Game, 1957-59 (Box 6)
  - Card Stunt at the Air Force Football Game, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Class Ranking, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Commencement 1968 (Box 6)
  - Commendations, 1966-68 (Box 6)
  - Conferences -- Misc. Policies, Problems, etc., 1955-64 (Box 6)
  - Conferences -- Off campus, 1966-69 (Box 6)
  - Conferences on Educational Objectives, 2/10/1969 (Box 6)
  - Conferences on Campus, 1968-69 (Box 6)
  - COOR. Council for Higher Education, 1965-68 (Box 6)
  - D (General), 1964-68 (Box 6)
  - Dean’s Council / Meetings, 1962-66 (Box 6)
  - Dedications, 1964-67 (Box 6)
  - Ditchley Conference, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Escondido Village, 1959-66 (Box 6)
  - Faculty Club, Stanford, 1966-68 (Box 6)
  - Fluoridation of Water Supply, 1968-69 (Box 6)
  - Fluoridation committee (never named) (Box 6)
  - Institute for Environmental Health, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Literary Studies at Stanford, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Invitations, 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Invitations to Speak (accepted), 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Invitations to Speak (regretted), 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Junior Faculty Forum, 1968 (Box 7)
  - McBride, Scott, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Midpeninsula Free University (non-current), 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Midpeninsula Observer, 1967-68 (Box 7)
  - National Defense Language Institute. Bad Boll, Germany – Reports from, 1960-61 (Box 7)
  - Pacific Eight (AAWU) Eligibility Petitions, Interpretations, 1966-68 (Box 7)
  - Parking (non-current), 1964-69 (Box 7)
  - Policy: Religion (background on change in policy – denominational worship on campus), 1965-66 (Box 7)
  - Policy: Retirements, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Policy: Use and Misuse of Stanford Name (Box 7)
  - Prince William (Box 7)
  - Questions, 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Sacramento Dinner for Stanford Alumni Legislators, 1964-68 (Box 7)
  - Sia, Cyril and Mrs. Cyril Sia (Summer Quarter Pres.) 1966-67 (Box 7)
  - Speakers, 1965-68 (Box 7)
  - Stanford Today and Tomorrow, 1966-68 (Box 7)
  - Stanford University Hospital, General Members, 1968-69 (Box 7)
  - Student Government Confrontation, 1965-66 (Box 7)
  - SLAC Scientific Policy Committee Meeting Minutes, 1962-68 (Box 7)
  - Timpany, Frederick P. 1959-65 (Box 7)
  - Tolos, Peter C., Research Associates, Inc., 1964-66 (Box 7)
  - Travel Grants, Inter-University Committee on, U. S. Dept. of State, 1964-69 (Box 8)
  - Trustee Committee Membership, 1964-69 (Box 8)
  - Trustees By-Laws (includes revisions made in 1963), 1947-64 (Box 8)
  - Trustees Campus Board meetings, 1966-68 (Box 8)
  - Trustees Meetings/Schedule/etc., 1965-68 (Box 8)
  - Trustee Nominations, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Trustees, Board of, President’s Annual Report to, 1965-67 (Box 8)
  - Tuition Exchange (Plan terminated 1969), 1964-69 (Box 8)
  - Tuition Waver, 1964-69 (Box 8)
  - Un-American Activities Committee. U.S. House and California State, 1960-61 (Box 8)
  - Un-American Activities Committee, clippings (Box 8)
  - Un-American Activities Committee "quotes" re (Box 8)
  - Un-American Activities Committee "Operation Abolition" (Box 8)
  - Un-American Activities Committee. U.S. House and California State, 1946-69 (Box 8)
  - USM -- High School Peace Groups, 1966 (Box 8)
  - University of California (Financial Aid Problem), 1966-69 (Box 8)
  - Upward Bound, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Vitae (Box 8)
  - Volunteer Services Center, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Walker, Gene (Trustee) (Box 8)
  - Watkins, Dean A. (Trustee) (Box 8)
  - Winds of Freedom Foundation, 1963-65 (Box 8)
  - Women's Social Regulations, 1965-68 (working papers during time of the revisional study made in 1966-67, important committee reports) (Box 8)
  - World Affairs Council, 1964-67 (Box 8)
- Stanford Research Institute, Series 4
  - Annual meeting, general members (Trustees), 1963-70 (Box 9)
  - Board of Directors, 1969-70 (Box 9)
  - Board of Trustees, SU, Proceedings before, April 30, 1969 (Box 9)
  - By-Laws and Articles of Incorporation, 1946-70 (Box 9)
  - Five-Year Plan, 1967-71 (Box 9)
  - International Building and Research Center, 1969 (Box 9)
  - International Industrial Conference, 1965-69 (Box 9)
  - National Priorities, Forum, Stanford-SRI Conferences, January 15-17, 1970 (terminated) (Box 9)
  - President Charles A. Anderson (Box 9)
  - SCL/Irvine Relocation Exhibit B, Summary Analysis, May 22, 1967 (Box 9)
  - Separation from Stanford (Box 9)
  - Stanford Relationship Policy, 1957-69 (SRI Coalition "urge that SRI be brought under closer control by the University," 1969) (Box 9)
  - Inquiries re: Sale of SRI, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Stanford Relationship, Relates to Change in Policy of, (Committee to Study Relationship), 1969-70 (Box 9)
  - SRI and Student Activism / Vietnam, 1967-69 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Two loose-leaf binders: List of Research Briefs 1-13, SRI Long Range Planning Service (Box 10)
  - "A Research Report by the Long Range Planning Service." SRI, Menlo Park, CA (Box 10)
  - #347 U.S. Color Television Guide, May 1968 (Box 10)
  - #349 Fire Loss Control, July 1968 (Box 10)
  - #350 Computer Programming, July 1968 (Box 10)
  - #351 Industrial Textiles, July 1968 (Box 10)
  - #352 Synthetic Fibers, August 1968 (Box 10)
  - #353 Air Pollution Control, August 1968 (Box 10)
  - #356 U. S. Government Data for Business Planner, September 1968 (Box 10)
  - #357 A Framework for Operations Planning, September 1968 (Box 10)
  - #358 Foamed Plastics, October 1968 (Box 10)
  - #360 Under the Sea, October 1968 (Box 10)
  - #361 The Changing Public Sector, November 1968 (Box 10)
  - #371 Trends in World Petrochemicals, April 1968 (Box 10)
  - #374 Fabricated Food, May 1969 (Box 10)
  - #375 Sectional Housing, May 1969 (Box 10)
  - Subject Index: Long Range Planning Reports, Sept. 1968 (Box 10)
  - Subject Index: Long Range Planning Reports, May 1968 (Box 10)
  - File Subject Headings for Long Range Planning Service Information Center (Box 10)
  - Report Impact Matrix, September 1968 (Box 10)